<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The infancy of elders a short treatise composed for vindication of the Christian liberty of freeborne denizens of England, or A refutation of the tyrannicall unlawfull mis-government of our church by lay-elders / written by J.S. minister of the Word in Lancashire.</title>
            <author>J. S., Minister of the Word in Lancashire.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S68</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8376</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11904437</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11904437</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50637</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62171)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50637)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 509:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The infancy of elders a short treatise composed for vindication of the Christian liberty of freeborne denizens of England, or A refutation of the tyrannicall unlawfull mis-government of our church by lay-elders / written by J.S. minister of the Word in Lancashire.</title>
                  <author>J. S., Minister of the Word in Lancashire.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50637:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50637:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE INFANCY OF ELDERS.</p>
            <p>A Short Treatiſe compoſed for Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Chriſtian liberty of Free-borne denizens of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR A Refutation of the Tyrannicall unlawfull miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government of our Church by Lay-Elders.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>J.S.</hi> Miniſter of the Word in <hi>Lancaſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 5.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Stand faſt therefore in the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made us free, and be not intangled againe with the yoke of bondage.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:50637:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50637:2"/>
            <head>The Infancy of Elders.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have long time exerciſed my patience in forbeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to write ſomething of this Subject, tryfling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way many dayes, in a tedious expectation, that ſome one better able, would have prevented me, who more fully and accurately (then I know my ſelf able to performe) might have perfected this worke: but ſeeing the daily incroaching tyranny of our new moduled Church Officers, ſpreading like Gangrenes over the whole body of the Kingdome, and none offering neither for ſafety to himſelfe, and his hereditary freedome, nor for prevention of evill to his brethren, to calterize, or take up a veine in them, to obſtruct this new dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous hot diſeaſe in our Eccleſiaſticall body; ſome though convinced in judgement that they are pernicious miſchiefes in a Kingdome, yet baſely fearing man more then God, forbeare to write againſt them; others partly Claſſicall, partly Epiſcopall, but really nothing, hove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring aloofe, with the reare-Mouſe to ſee the battell betwixt birds and beaſts, with reſolution to joyn with the ſtronger party, and now perceiving the Claſſes headily run on, forbearing to ſtop their proud carreer, like bruit beaſts, creepe into ſome crib, and there ſtop their mouths with meat, and thinke with dumbneſſe to fatten themſelves without giving teſtimony to the world of their humane reaſon; and indeed generally lulling themſelves in a ſottiſh ſilence, have made themſelves guilty thus farre of betraying their owne freedomes, to the irreverend cenſures of our new ſtamped Elders. I thought it my duty to ſhoot this poore paper bullet at them, which if it take no impreſſion upon them, yet I hope at the rebound, it may be taken up by ſome, who percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſoftneſſe of my Ammunition, will prepare harder ware againſt theſe impetuous furies, however it will be ſome evidence to future ages to procure a non-guilty upon my name, for traiterouſly conſenting to the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50637:3"/>ſubverſion of the furdamentall Lawes of this Kingdome, and betraying that liberty and freedome which as a Free-borne childe of God I ought to enjoy, into the hands of ignorant Tyrants; and like wiſe ſerve to free me from a brand of inſtability or wandring in my principles, ſuffering my ſelfe to bee toſſed too and fro with every puffe of wind: Know Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I am not of ſuch a Weather-cock temper as to bee moved from my well-grounded ſtation, though the North wind bluſter high, let others, who lately were of my opinion, till the magneticke force of earthly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment withdrew them, turne Hyperborean dotterells, and imitate the faſhions preſcribed them by holy Highlanders, whom the unſeaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſome late winters, forced Southward, more to ſuccour themſelves in a warmer clime, then out of any good intended to us natives; let ſuch I ſay play the Apes after them, ſetting up their holy forme of worſhip and Church-government, &amp; uſe the learned perſwaſions which a proud Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter (lately reputed a good man, whileſt ten pound <hi>per annum</hi> at a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chappell could ſatisfie him, but now having betroathed a Parliament mans ſiſter, is by the ſtrong cordage of attractive Apron-ſtrings drawne up a hill to a benefice of five hundred pound) labouring to draw his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory to the ſubſcription hereof, told them (whoſe bare aſſertions with his ruſticke Auditory paſſe for Oracles,) it was a government uſed in the Jewiſh Church, and therefore to be followed by us Chriſtians; Oh rare Pulpit Rhethoricke!</p>
            <p>It pities my heart to thinke how the poore Country people are miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by theſe blinde guides, who poore Simpletons, perceiving the current of the times, are many of them troubled (having plumbeous head-pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) to ſhape their Pulpit ſtuffe according to the humor thereof, in which they take more paines for ſaving their benefices, then their peoples ſoules: you can ſcarcely goe to heare a Sermon but the ſubject thereof is obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to this godly government; and the Presbyterian fatlings will blatter out, and quote almoſt every verſe in the Bible that hath but the word El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in it, to prove its lawfulneſſe thereby; theſe ſilly <hi>quondam</hi> Sur-Johns, but now Presbyter or Preſter Johns Parochiall Princes, doe more Lord it over Gods heritage, then ever <hi>Becket, Wolſey</hi> or <hi>Laud</hi> did: inſtead of fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, leading their flocks into captivity, forcing ſubmiſſions to their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious rules, contrary to the doctrine and late profeſſions of moſt of them, and avouch Authority from the Parliament for to juſtifie their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings herein, and proclaime commiſſion for each one to be <hi>ſummus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdos ſui Claſſis;</hi> and the Elderſhip to bee Officers of the Church of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50637:3"/>Chriſt by Authority of both Houſes of Parliament; and who dare ſay againſt it?</p>
            <p>I am loath to ſet perine to paper to claſh againſt any thing debated and concluded in that High and Honourable Court, having hitherto laboured to my power, to propagate their cauſe, which Cauſe was proteſted to bee and expreſly ſet downe in the Covenant, that it was the defence of his Majeſtics perſon, the Proteſtant Religion, the fundamentall Lawes and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Subject, and to endeavour Reformation of Religion in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> according to the holy word; but now they having ſet up a Government, not agreeable to Gods word, nor conſiſtant with the fundamental Lawes of this Kingdome (as I ſhall ſhew you anon) I reſolving with my ſelf that it was better to obey God then man, did for prevention of further miſleading captive poore ſoules, for ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of ſome men wavering in opinion, for diſcharging of my owne conſcience, and for inſtructing, not correcting the Honourable Parliament, in hopes to adde ſome good ſoules to the number of thoſe honeſt Patriots, who were but by few out-voted in the ſetling of this Antichriſtian government, and in hopes to worke heereby a peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and legall quaſhing of the ſame, adventure to publiſh this paper, wherein I ſhall endeavour to anatomize this giddy government, and ſhew its illegality, which undertaking if I erre through ignorance, I will upon convincement from better judgement, grounded upon ſound divinity and reaſon, willingly recant my miſtakes, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to, and allow of a warrantable Elderſhip: In the meane time I crave pardon for a little freedome of language.</p>
            <p>It may perchance be wondered at by ſome, that I being not of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry grave yeares my ſelfe, ſhould dare to write any thing againſt the Grandees &amp; Seniors of our times; but we have a Proverb amongſt us, That old men are twice children; and truly ſuch are many, of our El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: they may perchance as babes deſire the ſincere milke of the word; but I am ſure many of them are not as yet growne thereby, <hi>(ſed nucibus relictis)</hi> I intend to have about with them armed to their beſt advantage, admitting them their ſage and politique capacities as El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and yet will take them off their feet, and throw them upon their backes ere I leave them. In proſecution whereof, though it be not my cuſtome to play with words; yet for method ſake, I will firſt inſiſt u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the definition of the word Elders, <hi>Omnis enim qui de re aliqua in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituitur ſorme debes à definitione proficiſci, ut intelligatur quid fit de quo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50637:4"/>diſputatur,</hi> and prove that our Lay-Elders are no waies to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the things ſignified by the word.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of Civill Elders in generall, and that here in <hi>England,</hi> our Lay-Elders are not within that notion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, of Spirituall Elders in generall, and that they cannot be rightly taken for ſuch.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that Civill Elders are not to joyne with Spirituall in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall affaires.</p>
            <p>For the definition of the word Elder, <hi>Verſtegan</hi> and divers others affirme, that it is an abreviation of a word which we borrow from the Saxons, called <hi>Salden ealder,</hi> which word is uſed for grave, wiſe, and expert men; men which for their deſerving parts, excellent above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, were made choice of to be Officers in the Common-wealth, or elſe for ſuch their noble deſervings, were promoted to dignity and honour: And hence hath that cuſtome growne in <hi>England,</hi> That out of the Nobility were ſelected the moſt diſcreet, and grave Barons, and were made above the ranke of Barons, Ealdermen. In the Daniſh tongue <hi>Eorles</hi> in Engliſh <hi>Erles,</hi> a name we continue to this day: And indeed Erles and Elders are both one in the literall ſenſe.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe we have in every ancient Burrow, a Court of Ealder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that is to ſay Elders, men of moſt ſufficiency and diſcretion, and theſe men were to bee honoured of others for their worthy and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vertues; according to which Mr. <hi>Purchaſe</hi> in his booke called His Pilgrimage, fol. 125. faith, The Iewes have an affirmative precept (to wit) riſe before thine Elder, the word Elder being expounded in that place by <hi>Rabbi Joſe,</hi> ſaith, it ſignifieth a wiſe man, though young in yeares, and to him the people were to riſe at foure cubits diſtance, and being paſt to ſit downe againe: according to this interpretation, my Lord <hi>Cooke</hi> that grave and reverend Judge of the Law, in the firſt part of his Inſtitutes, <hi>fol.</hi> 168. ſaith, <hi>Aldermani non ita dicuntur propter aetatem, ſed propter ſapientiam, &amp; dignitatem, adoleſcentes exim eſſent ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris periti &amp; experti.</hi> But ſtay, I muſt not digreſſe too far from my buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; for what doth this concerne our reverend Coblers, Webſters, Taylors, Skinners, &amp;c? the Ruling-Elders of this age, to whom I am ſure the ſenſe of this word is not applicable, unleſſe in reference to their Trades and Handicrafts; and yet theſe filly upſtart fellows now made Lay-Elders, begin to puffe and ſwell already with pride, and conceit themſelves by a wonderfull providence to be exalted above
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50637:4"/>their former equalls expecting ſubmiſſion from the people as unto Rulers: for my part I ſhall acquit them of this crime, and give my voice that the poore ſimple bumpkins are not to be blamed for it; it being according to their education and tutoring; for ſith their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter or High Prieſt tells them, that their government was uſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Jewes, well may they expect the circumſtance or conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitance of their office, to follow along with the office it ſelfe (to wit) that according to the Jewiſh cuſtome the people ſhould riſe up before them.</p>
            <p>But this is not all that cauſeth this timpany of pride in them, they are further inſtructed, that they ſhall reap profit by their places, the ſame or more (their territories conſidered,) as Biſhops formerly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted from the people.</p>
            <p>Now this conſidered, me thinkes, the people have very much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed their liberty, who gave any conſent to this government; for that whereas formerly the greedy gripings of Biſhops and their offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, were cenſured for high incroachments, upon the peoples pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges and freedomes, and propriety in their goods, they muſt needs now expect a huge multiplication of extortion, from a numerous rable of Lay-Elders, poore and meane fellowes put into Office, who being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from their Trades and Handicrafts, which was their livelihood, muſt now of neceſſity live upon the people. But I will proceed to a further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of the word.</p>
            <p>The word Elder is ſometimes taken for aged and hoary headed men, as Levit. the 19. cap. the 32. ver. our Engliſh tranſlation renders it <hi>thou ſhalt riſe before up the hoary headed;</hi> And the 1 of Tim. 5.1. It is uſed for a word of Age, not Office, and all tranſlations of ſuch places render it Senior not Presbiter, <hi>rebuke not an Elder,</hi> tranſlated by <hi>Beza,</hi> by <hi>Junius &amp; Tremeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, ſeniore non increpato,</hi> by <hi>Eraſmus, ſeniorem ne ſavius objurges,</hi> but all <hi>ſeniorem,</hi> not <hi>Preſbiterem. Intreate him as a Father, the yong men as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> It is likewiſe a word of age, the 1 of Pet. the 5.1. <hi>The Elders which are among you I exhort, &amp;c.</hi> and ver. 5. <hi>likewiſe yee yonger ſubmit your ſelves unto the elder,</hi> but in this latter place, it is a word both of Office and Age. Peter bidding them <hi>feed the flocke,</hi> and therefore is the word there rendred <hi>Presbyteri,</hi> as it is alwaies where it ſignifies Church Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers (but not comprehenſible of lay Elders, of which anone) in all other places it is rendred <hi>ſeniores.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reader what is in other Countryes I cannot tell, but in this County of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50637:5"/>ours, in which theſe Maſter-ſhips Country Lay-Elders are leapt into Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority (upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a private petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſome lordly Paſtors, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> never heard of by many thouſands, till the Ordinance came downe) I know not any one parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular man of them that is compriſed within the ſence of the word, that is to be a hoary headed man, but they are generally as non-ſenſically cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Elders in this interpretation, as they come ſhort for challenging the name in the firſt, (to wit) grave, wiſe, and expert.</p>
            <p>Since God hath ſet theſe fellowes over us as a puniſhment for our ſins, and a meere reproach unto the Nation, that men ſhould rule over us that are not endowed with any thing to be honoured in them, no not ſo much as with this, which their <hi>Muſe Dame nature,</hi> amongſt the reſt of their Arts, ſhe hath quallified them with, might eaſily have beſtowed u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them; but I will proceed a little further in expreſſion of the Word, and ſee if it will any wiſe concerne them.</p>
            <p>The word Elder ſometimes is a word of Eccleſiaſticall Office, and not of age, and is as much as to ſay Prieſt or Biſhop, and is ſcarce mentioned in the new Teſtament in any other ſence, unleſſe Mathew the 26.3. Math. 16.21. Jo. 11.47. where it is rendred <hi>Elders of the people,</hi> which all Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors render <hi>ſeniores:</hi> in other places it is tranſlated Presbyter <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which in the Greeke ſignifies <hi>ſeniores aetate, Magis priſci qui Eccleſia pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt,</hi> the word being derived of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Legatus mittor</hi> to be ſent an Embaſſadour, and this expoſition I take to be moſt agreeable to the word of God, Paul telling us in the ſecond to the Corinthians 5.20. that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel are Chriſts Embaſſadours, praying us by the Goſpel to be reconciled to God: and 6. Epheſ. 20. <hi>Paul though in Priſon was Chriſts Embaſſadour to speake the word boldly;</hi> ſo that according to the ſence of the word Presbyter, Lay-Elders are not to be underſtood therby, only the Miniſters of the Goſpel, the Embaſſadours of Chriſt; ſometime the word Elder is rendred <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is <hi>inspectores,</hi> overſeers <hi>of their flocke,</hi> Acts the 20.28. and in that Chapter it is both rendred Presbyter in the 17. ver. and <hi>Epiſcopus</hi> or Overſeer in the 28. <hi>Sunt enim Epiſcopi ſacri gregis in spectores qui verbo &amp; gubernationi preerunt qui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quaſi ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores in doctrinam &amp; mores commiſſi gregis inquirebant.</hi> Nor are out Lay-Elders within the compriſe or reach of this word, for they have no flocks to feede, their high Prieſt takes that Office to himſelfe. And I thinke they will thanke me for telling them ſo, for they would hate to be called Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</p>
            <p>And here by the way I thinke it were not amiſſe ſhould I a little ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plane
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50637:5"/>the meaning of that much wreſted and abuſed Text of Scripture which our Novaliſts ſo much inſiſt upon, to enſnare the people to a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to their new Elderſhip, 1 Tim. 5.17. <hi>The Elders which rule well account worthy of double honour, especially thoſe which labour in word and doctrine,</hi> by which Text they would perſwade the people, that there ought to be ruling Lay-Elders as well as teaching Elders in the Church.</p>
            <p>The Elders in that place is by all Tranſlators rendered <hi>Presbyteri,</hi> not <hi>ſeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ores,</hi> Lay-Elders or Rulers of the people, but I ſay <hi>Presbyteri,</hi> that is Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the goſpel, Embaſſadours of Chriſt; ſo that it cannot be underſtood of ruling Laity; but ruling or governing Cleargy; nor is this interpretation, either contrary to Gods word, as may be proved by other Texts ef Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor doth it any wiſe gainſay the practiſe of the Primitive Churches, for you may finde it recorded in <hi>Poſen. in vita Auguſti, cap.</hi> 5. that there may be as well ruling Miniſters; as preaching Miniſters, for ſome for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sacraments, for their wiſdome and judgement were not unmeete to be Biſhops and Paſtors, and yet being not well verſed in the languge of the people over which they had the charge they wanted elocution to preach, and yet governed their Church well, as <hi>Valerius</hi> was a Biſhop amongſt the Romans, at that time <hi>Paul</hi> writ to <hi>Tymothy,</hi> and being a Grecian borne, and not skilled to pronounce the Latine, did not preach, and yet was honoured as a reverend Father of the Church, and Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt; ſo I beleeve wee have ſome great Presbyters rule in Welch Benefices, and know not how to teach in that language, and yet will think to have double honour from their Pariſhoners, and it is due un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, but if they could teach too, then were they more to be eſteemed.</p>
            <p>Wee may read in the firſt of the Cor. 12. chap. <hi>All men had not the ſame gifts, to one was given the spirit of wiſdome, to another the spirit of faith, to another the ſpirit of healing, to another the ſpirit of miracles, to another di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers kinds of tongues,</hi> and ver. 28 It is ſaid in the Church God hath ſet ſome, <hi>firſt Apoſtles, ſecondly. Prophets, and thirdly Teachers;</hi> ſo that if wee muſt goe the old way of expounding Scripture, to examine one place by another, wee may hence cleerely perceive, that that Text of <hi>Tymothy</hi> is to be underſtood, ruling Presbyters, and not ruling Lay-Elders; ruling Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters ordained by God and his Church, and all Tranſlators that ever I did ſee render it Preebyter, underſtanding that the Elders which rule well, <hi>and are to be accounted worthy of double honour,</hi> mentioned in that Text, are ſpirituall men, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Miniſters of the Goſpel, Chriſts Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:50637:6"/>
            <p>But admit the new Claſſicall wreſting of that Text, that it is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of ruling Laiety; yet there can be nothing gathered from that pace to prove that ſuch men are to meddle in Eccleſiaſticall affaires, (but of that in his proper place) only that the Civill Elders, which governed the State well, were to be accounted worthy of double honour; but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the ſpirituall Elders which governed the Church, and increaſed the flocke of Chriſt by their word and doctrine.</p>
            <p>I have briefly done with the firſt part of this worke, to wit, the diffini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the word Elder, and now I will proceed to the ſecond branch touching Civil, or Lay-Elders in generall, in the number of whom our Lay-Elders are not to be reckoned.</p>
            <p>Wee read that Jewiſh State was governed by Elders, almoſt in every Authour, which writes any thing either of them, their State or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and more particularly and fully Mr. <hi>Purchaſe</hi> in his Pilgrimage, <hi>fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio</hi> 110. teſtifieth of them thus, That their government was under 70. El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders according to the number of the perſons which deſcended with Jacob into Aegypt, and that the 70 aſſigned after to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the 11. chapter of Numbers, were but continued in their former Office, with confirmation from on high, but not newly inſtituted, and ruled in Aegypt, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Pharaohs</hi> cruelty, and were by <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aron aſſembled together,</hi> Exod 4.29.</p>
            <p>And thus it continued in <hi>Joſuahs</hi> time, till they had conquered and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited ſeverall Cities, then each City had its Sanhedrim or Councell of Elders, proportionable to the greatneſſe thereof; as in Bethlem <hi>Boaz</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled 10 Elders about the matter of <hi>Ruth,</hi> Ruth 4.2. 1 Chron. 23.4. 2 Chron. 19.8. and uſually every Senate of Elders had a Levite or two to ſit with them in judgement, becauſe the Elders were ignorant of the Talmud or Law which was much altered, and inlarged by ſeverall Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the Univerſity of Jeruſalem, and was laſtly compleated by <hi>Rabbi Jochanan, Anno Chriſti,</hi> 500. and called the Talmud, a rule in all cauſes Eccleſiaſticall and Civill to this very day, amongſt the Jewes.</p>
            <p>God commanded Moſes in the 11 of Numbers, ſaying, <hi>Gather unto me</hi> 70. <hi>men of the Elders of Iſrael, which thou knoweſt to be Elders of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and they ſhall be are the burden of the people, with thee</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This is a place much inſiſted upon to warrant our newtaking of Elders into the Church, to beare part of the Government; but I will make it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that this part of Scripture is no warrant for us to doe ſo heere in England.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:50637:6"/>
            <p>The Government thus ſetled, ſaith <hi>Joſephus</hi> in his book of Antiquities, <hi>libro quarto, cap.</hi> 8. was mixed the Monarchy being in <hi>Moſes,</hi> but qualified with an ariſtocracy in the 70, and democracy (as it were) appeared in the often Aſſemblies of the people: &amp; this but continued, ſaith he, till they deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a King, and then it ceaſed; and whilſt it continued, it was only for tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall affaires, the Elders not being to medle in any Eccleſiaſticall matter, for Levites only ſate with them, becauſe they were learned in the Talmud; not that of right it belonged unto them to ſit there. <hi>Goodwin</hi> in his Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſh Antiquities <hi>fol.</hi> 199. and 198. he ſaith, how <hi>Jehoſophat</hi> appointed in every walled City ſecular Judges, which were their Elders to determine criminall offences.</p>
            <p>I wonder that our Presbyterians ſhould be ſo far brazed with igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as not to bluſh to urge this portion of Scripture for a warrant for their Court of Elders to be ſet up here in England, when as it failes in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular, to be any wiſe applicable to us: for,</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Jewes were governed by 70 Elders before; ſo was never En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</p>
            <p>Seconly, <hi>Moſes</hi> was both King and Prieſt among them; he was their Prieſt, and tooke great paines in his holy function with them, whereby he became leſſe fitted to manage their civill affaires; and wee may likewiſe reade, Deut. 33.5. <hi>Moſes was among the righteous as King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I never knew that our Biſhops or Presbyters ever exerciſed any Kingly Office in England, nor hath it ever been, unleſſe in theſe foure yeeres laſt paſt, whenas, <hi>Charles Stewart</hi> being gone from his Parliament, and being denudated of his Kingly power, which power in conceit fell into the laps of our Aſſembly, who thereupon Enthuſiaſtically, by imaginary Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, publiſh, they muſt take to themſelves Elders of the people to beare part of the burthen with them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that was Gods owne immediate Act, and he put his ſpirit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and they propheſied verſe the 25; but this is a meere humane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution not warranted by any meanes, unleſſe by ſuch imaginary Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and ſtrange Oracles, which things ſince Chriſt himſelfe came in the fleſh have ceaſed, and why ſhould wee now credit them?</p>
            <p>I beleeve our Elders are not by their Office made wiſer, or indowed with any ſupernaturall gifts at all, but continue ſtill, though Mr. Elders; yet as arrant blockheads as they were before; ſo that a man may ſay of them as one ſayd of an ignorant Judge, ſitting in his robes upon the Bench, yonder Judge is made fine by his place, his place not beautified
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50637:7"/>him, nor for my part will I beleeve any thing they can propheſie, unleſſe they tell me they will be kickt out of their Office.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that Government ceaſed, when Iſrael obtained a King, and now that England hath, and ever had a King, what ſhall wee doe with this inconſiſtant Government? Unleſſe to fit our ſelves to entertaine the Elderſhip, wee caſt off Monarchicall Government, and introduce a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by States; for my part I wiſh that hand to wither that ſhall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to lop off the royall branches of our Land, whoſe right to the Crowne, and Kingly prerogative, are equally juſt to any Subject his poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing what he hath, nor is there any underſtanding Chriſtian, reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully called Independant of any other opinion; ſo he may enjoy the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his owne conſcience without Civill coercion in point of Religion, he being to give an account to God of his owne ſoule; and every one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to beare his owne burthen, <hi>the Father not being to anſwer for the Son, nor the Son for the Father.</hi> Gal. 6.5. Ezek. 18.20. but in civill and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall matters is ready to ſubject himſelfe with the moſt ſubmiſſive to Kingly Authority, according to the Law of the Nation where he lives; And may thoſe curſed ſoules who contrive the obliterating of the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous beings of our Kings heere, be ſuddainely ſnached hence by a hand un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looked for; and yet I wiſh King <hi>Charles</hi> his returning to his Parliament, and hearkening to their wholſome Councells, for therein I conceive his flouriſhing and happineſſe will moſt conſiſt.</p>
            <p>That there are, and hath been Civill Elders here and elſewhere, no man needs to doubt, it is obvious enough, and manifeſt to each capacity; our Judges at Weſtminſter are nothing elſe, but in this ſence Elders and Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to ſit in Counſell to determine and judge of criminall and other civill affaires, which wee continue ſtill to this day: Therefore are our new Lay-Elders in this ſence uſeleſſe: and if wee muſt for other ends erect Jewiſh Sanhedrins in England, I have ſhewed you it is not warrantable for us ſo to doe, becauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> by Gods ſpeciall appointment aſſembled 70. Elders to beare part of the Government with him, although it were urged with all the wit, zeale and fervency, it's poſſible for a Countrey Presbyter to palliate his people from his Pulpit with, yet his labour is all in vaine, and he but endeavours to juſtifie unwarrantable things, when as the unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sophiſter, cannot ſet a ſpecious gloſſe on a good matter.</p>
            <p>But perhaps he hath learned his leſſon ſo far by rote, as to tell the people it was in Europe, firſt ſet up at Geneva by reverend Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> and ſince embraced by the States of Holland, and ſeverall places of Germany, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50637:7"/>therefore why ſhould not wee have it in England?</p>
            <p>I anſwer in the ſame way of reaſon that in Rome is and hath beene a long time continued the Popiſh Religion, and profeſſed, and maintained by the Emperour, by the Kingdome of Spaine, by the King of France, and ſome Princes of Germany, and therefore why ſhould not we profeſſe that Religion too? But more particularly to take off this cavill, I will make it appeare that that argument doth no waies concerne England.</p>
            <p>The beginning of this Government at Geneva is well knowne, was by Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> framed; yet if wee will beleeve Hiſtories, not intended: for he perceiving the abuſes, and too predominating tyranny of Biſhops con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Gods word, Lording it over Gods Heritage, deviſed a way for freeing the people from that ſlavery, and the inlarging of Gods people, to caſt off the Hierarchicall yoke, and ſo invented a new way, which he knew the giddy multitude (greedy of novelties) would be eaſily fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinated with, and that the rather becauſe they groaned under the heavy preſſure of their former ſlavery; wherefore he buzzed into the eares of the people that they ſhould have none of theſe Lording Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, but they ſhould be ruled by every Paſtor in his reſpective Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and to ſubmit to his cenſure, and becauſe all ſhould not hang on ſo ſlender a thread as the likeing of an ignorant multitude, he bound the people by oath to give obedience to ſuch orders as he with two other Miniſters (for more grace to the buſineſſe) had ſet downe, and appointed every Church being to be governed by it ſelfe, and the people ſworne to obedience, and ſo every Church almoſt differing from other began to accuſe one another of diſobedience to the will of Chriſt in thoſe things in which they differed, which occaſioned much ſtrife and contentions among them: for theſe Presbyters being men of fleſh as well as the Biſhop was, and ſubject to the like infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, began to flutter as much or more over the people, as ever the Biſhop did, and to exerciſe as much coercive power over mens con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; wherefore the people ſeeing themſelves nothing bettered by this new frame of government, but unadviſedly they had conſented to a multiplication of tyranny; and that whereas formerly they had but one Biſhop, which did ſomething extort upon them, they now had a company of ignorant Presbyters, which did much outvie the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop in domineering power over them, they then began to champe u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the bit they had taken into their mouthes, and began to mutiny a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> who together with his two aſſociats, the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50637:8"/>of the people to embrace, and the contrivers of this kind of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, were in the heate of theſe diſcontents baniſhed the Towne.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> was now put to his ſhifts to appeaſe this tumult, and when he had caſt upon all aſſaies, he concluded none ſo probable, to take effect, as to admit ſome of the Citizens to joyne in government with the Presbyters, and ſo they might perhaps admit him with his new device of Presbyterian Miniſtry into the City againe, which fell out accordingly; for a few yeeres after the Citizens of Geneva had baniſhed <hi>Calvin</hi> (ſaith juditious <hi>Hooker</hi>) in his preface to his booke intituled, Eccleſiaſticall policy, ſuch was the levity and inconſtancy of thoſe people, ſome places being in the interim fallen voide, and in want of a Miniſter, that they were not ſo willing to be rid of <hi>Calvin</hi> before, as they were now importunate to have him backe againe, and with ſeverall letters and ingagements did court him to returne unto them; <hi>Calvin</hi> conſidered with himſelfe, that now was the time to make knowne unto them, he would be no more tennant at will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them; but if they would have him to be their Teacher againe, they muſt be content to admit a compleate forme of Diſcipline, which both they and their Paſtors ſhould be ſworne to obſerve for ever after, of which Diſcipline the maine and principall parts were theſe; a ſtanding Eccleſiaſticall Court to be eſtabliſhed, perpetuall Judges in that Court to be their Miniſters, others of the people anu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally choſen (twice ſo many as they) to be Judges together with them in the ſame Court: And theſe two ſorts to have power over mens manners, to determine all kinde of Eccleſiaſticall cauſes, and to puniſh as far as with excommunication, all ſorts of people.</p>
            <p>This propoſition of his did ſome what trouble them, for they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered that this government was little better then Popiſh Tyranny, preſented to them under a new forme; for though for every Miniſter there were two Lay-men to fit and give voice in the Eccleſiaſticall conſiſtory; yet they feared that the filling up of thoſe ſeates was but to pleaſe the minde of the people, to thinke their owne ſway ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, when as things were to come to tryall, their Paſtors learning would over perſwade ſimple people, who knowing the time of their Preſidentſhip to be but ſhort, would alwaies ſtand in feare of their Miniſters perpetuall authority; but notwithſtanding theſe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſuch were the ſtraits the Citizens had brought themſelves into
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50637:8"/>through their owne giddineſſe, that now they muſt of neceſſity im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace <hi>Calvin</hi> upon theſe or any other conditions, unleſſe to their endleſſe diſgrace, they would with ridiculous lightneſſe diſmiſſe him whom they had with all earneſtneſſe, and after an importunate, and moſt urgent manner deſired to returne unto them; wherefore having driven themſelves upon theſe exigents, they admit of Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> and his compound conſiſtory, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1541. And here was the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning amongſt Chriſtians of Lay-Elders in their Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which you may perceive [Reader] through neceſſity by a in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant people in a troubled State was accepted of.</p>
            <p>Now good morrow to your Infant worſhip, good Mr. Lay-Elder, or rather your ſpurious brat of a Geneva brable; I muſt tell you, you may be a handſome fellow, but you looke ill favouredly in an Engliſh habit; but may you ſay unto me, your Taylor or High Prieſt was too blame (for no ſtrange thing now a dayes for Taylor and Prieſt to meet in one perſon) to put you into the Engliſh mode: Let me tell you in your owne Country Phraſe, you beſeeme your Office, as a Sowe beſeemes a ſaddle, you looke as ſtrangely amongſt us as an Owle at noone day; you muſt not thinke to make us daire under you, weele rather like a flocke of little birds fright and chaſe you backe againe to your Arabian Deſart; when wee come to Geneva, weele be governed by you, in the meane time wee do not deſire you ſhould governe us: nor indeede becauſe you are ſo rightly entertained in Geneva, and Holland, are you fit gueſts for us. For Geneva was a free City governed by Elders, and Towne Burgers before ever Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> came there, who admitted ſome of thoſe Aldermen yearely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Claſſis, &amp; there were ſome little more collour for that govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment amongſt us, if our Judges, Juſtices, &amp; Aldermen might be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into your reſpective Claſſes; but there is no ſuch matter in our new Elderſhip, but the moſt ſilly fellowes generally are pitched u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon to make Lay-Elders of; and truely this is the greateſt peece of pollicy I have obſerved from our Presbyter, or High Prieſts in our Country, for by this meanes they themſelves will rule the roaſt, the Lay-Elders being meere <hi>Jacks</hi> to be wound up and downe at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and the better to compaſſe this their ends and deſigne, ſome of them have wronged and abuſed the Parliament, in nominating unto them, tryars for the ſufficiency of the Elders, to be choſen in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Claſſes, ſo inſufficient and ignorant that cannot write their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50637:9"/>owne names, the beſt knowledge they have being to miſreade a little Engliſh, and this I am informed was done by the preſent Incombent at Standiſhe and ſome others; nay more then ſo, when the Ordinance came downe, and that ſuch men were by the Parliament appointed tryars to be Lay-Elders themſelves, which the people not mindfull to thwart any thing the Parliament by the mouth of their Miniſter deſired, voted it ſo, and ſo they were Judges themſelves, and the parties to be judged of themſelves: Like as if a Juſtice were made a Jaylor, or a Marſhall, ſhould commit a Souldier: To commit a man to himſelfe which is againſt the rules of Law and reaſon; but no more of this, I conceive that this go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment being ſet up at Geneva, is no preſident imitable for England, only I thinke it were not amiſſe to follow their faſhion a little before in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangling of our ſelves) in this; That ſeing our fundamentall Lawes in Church ſubverted, and our liberties betrayed into the hands of Lay-El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders (for whoſe government there is no warrant in Scripture, I meane their governing Eccleſiaſticall affaires) Wee ſhould rowſe up a godly ſpirit in our ſelves, and doe as the then free Citizens did by the dominee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Presbyters in Geneva, baniſhing them thence: I ſay wee ſhould kicke theſe Caterpillars out of our Kingdome, and ſweeping this rubbiſh from the doores of our Temples, and whipping theſe money changers thence, beate the fellowes into their old trades and handicrafts againe.</p>
            <p>It might I am confident procure ſome more warrantable and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate government then this, which I refer to the ſerious conſideration of our wiſe Parliament, in hopes their wiſdomes will take due care to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the impending miſeries of our Nation, for very many thouſands will rather have moderate Epiſcopacy up, then this ſenſeleſſe government of Lay-Elders, which are indeede no Rulers, but meere ſtalking Horſes or Aſſes, or a diſguiſe wherein the Presbyters may plunder the people of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of conſcience, pretending it is not the Art of Cleargy only; pritty judgling; but no more of this, <hi>ſtultum eſt obſurdas opiniones accuratius refellere,</hi> I will proceede to treate of that part or diviſion of this worke lies next in order, to wit of ſpirituall Elders in generall, and that our Lay-Elders may not rightly be taken for ſuch.</p>
            <p>Every Biſhop, Presbyter, Paſtor, or other grave and reverend Divine, is rightly and truely called a ſpirituall Elder, and to prove this my aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I neede not wander far to fetch authority from rare Authors; the Apoſtles themſelves have ſaved me a labour, as Peter the 1.5.1. <hi>The El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders which are among you I exhort who am alſo an Elder, &amp;c.</hi> John in his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50637:9"/>2. and 3. Epiſtles ſtiles himſelfe and Elder; in the ſecond thus, <hi>The Elder unto the elect Lady:</hi> in the third <hi>The Elder unto the welbeloved Gains:</hi> and wee may reade Acts 6.6. becauſe the word of God ſhould not be left, and the people, to ſerve tables, wherefore the Apoſtles deſired the people to <hi>looke out among themſelves</hi> 7 <hi>men of honeſt report, full of the Holy Ghoſt, and of wiſedome whom they admitted into holy Orders by praying and laying on of hands,</hi> who were called Elders; ſo Paul Acts 14.23. when he paſſed through ſeverall Countries upon his being ſtoned at Lyſtra in Licaonia, ordained them Elders in every Church, Elders in that place by all Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators being rendred Presbyters or Biſhops, men of holy Orders to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the Apoſtles, who being thereunto thus lawfully called, have Gods promiſe <hi>to let his holy spirit reſt upon them even unto the end of the world,</hi> Math. 28.20. It being promiſed to ſuch as teache his people to obſerve all things, <hi>whatſoever I have commanded you, even to ſuch who had Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to teach all Nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the holy Ghoſt.</hi> Wee may reade likewiſe Iames 5.14. <hi>If any be ſicke among you, let him ſend for the Elders of the Church, and let him pray over him, anointing him with oyle in the name of the Lord;</hi> the word Elder being there tranſlated Presbyter, which is of the ſame ſignification with us, as <hi>Sacerdos</hi> was under the Law. There are many more places of Scripture to prove ſpirituall Elders in the Church; But I will briefely ſhut up this point with the 20 of the Acts, where it appeares, how Paul at <hi>Melitum called the Elders from Epheſus,</hi> verſe the 27. and telling them <hi>that they muſt ſee his face no more,</hi> he charges them verſe the 28. <hi>that they ſhould take heede unto themſelves, and to all the flocke over which the holy Ghoſt had made them Biſhops to feede the Church of God;</hi> by all which, and other Texts of Scripture, it is evident that the word Elder generally in the new Teſtament, ſignifies feeding and praying Miniſters, not loyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, lazie, Lay-Elders, Officers no more requiſite in a Church, then a company of drones are uſefull in a hive of Bees; unneceſſary evills, meere horſeleeches to ſucke the peoples bloud, who have no neede of Phleboto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; but I leave the Jewiſh Laiety, which I hope will no waies arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate this Office unto themſelves, though their holy Fathers, their high Prieſts endued with great ſtore of impudence, and ignorance, tells them they are inſtated into holy Orders by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, when with hands lifted up at their elections they tooke the Covenant, by which Covenant I would have them to underſtand, they are to degrade themſelves from their Office, for it being on foote in Scotland, is no warrant for them to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50637:10"/>continue it heere in England, the words of the Covenant being, That wee ſhall endeavour the reformation of Religion in the Church of England, according to Gods holy word: and I cannot finde one Text in Scripture to warrant their calling in the Church, they being Lay-men; nor will that argument which ſome frame from the Levites, having ſeverall places of truſt about the Temple, ſerve to prove their Office and Government.</p>
            <p>It is true that in <hi>Moſes</hi> time, <hi>Gerſhon Cohath, and Merari, Levy</hi> his three Sons, had the Office to pitch, to take downe, and to beare up and downe the Tabernacle, and the veſſells thereof: the Gerſhouites charge was to carry the coverings and hangings of the Tabernacle: the Coha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thites the chiefe things within the Sanctuary: and the Merarites had charge of the wood-workes, and the reſt of the inſtruments of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle; This was their Office during their abode in the Wilderneſſe, whilſt they were on their Journey, but afterwards when they were ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the promiſed Land, <hi>David</hi> changed their Office, ſome being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to have charge of the Treaſure of the Temple, 1 Chron. 26.20. others to be Overſeers and Judges, others to be Porters and Singers, 1 Chron. 23.4. The <hi>Singers were to be clad in linnen robes,</hi> 2 Chron. 5.12. hence doe ſome argue that the government by Elders, is no more then what was in <hi>Davids</hi> time, when the Levites were.</p>
            <p>The Levites were Judges and Overſeers, to which objection I give this anſwer.</p>
            <p>God by his divine and eternall decree had appointed the <hi>Tribe of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi to ſerve at his Alter, and miniſter unto the people;</hi> as wee finde it recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the 10 of Deut. verſe 8. God ſeperated <hi>the Tribe of Levi to beare the Arke of the Covenant of the Lord, and to ſtand before the Lord to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter unto him, and to bleſſe in his name even to this day.</hi> And Deut. 11. and the 5. <hi>The Lord thy God hath choſen him out of all thy Tribes to ſtand and miniſter in the name of the Lord, him and his ſons for ever.</hi> And <hi>Moſes</hi> in the 33 of Deut. verſe 8. <hi>prayes, That the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim and Thummim of the Lord be with thine holy One,</hi> meaning in that place one of the Tribe of Levi, who verſe the 10, <hi>ſhall teach Jacob thy Judgements, and Iſrael thy Law: they ſhall put insenſe before thy face, and burnt offrings upon thine Altar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is manifeſt by thoſe places of Scripture, that it was Gods holy will that the Tribe of Levi ſhould ſerve at his Altar, all of them being inſtated in holy orders, by impoſition of hand; and although amongſt them there were certaine degrees according to which <hi>Paul</hi> writ in the 1 to Tim. 3.13. that they that have miniſtred well, get themſelves a good degree, as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50637:10"/>
               <hi>Godwyn</hi> in his Jewiſh Antiquities <hi>fol.</hi> 22 obſerves, as when they had been a moneth initiated, they were to be preſented unto God, Numb. 3.15. and they were conſecrated by impoſition of hands, at 25 yeeres old, Num. 8.24. And they were to carry the Tabernacle up &amp; downe from 30 to 50, and afterwards they were to overſee and inſtruct the yonger Levites in the manner of Biſhops; but they were from the firſt to be inſtated in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Orders, and then capable to be Overſeers or Biſhops as they laboured to get a good degree.</p>
            <p>Now I preſume none will be ſo ſilly as to follow our new Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Doctrine, which perſwade that our government in Church by Lay-Elders, is no more but this, which our highly beneficed Brethren cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud in their Pulpits: For know, Reader, there is no Analogy betwixt the Levites and Lay-Elders. For firſt God appointed the one to ſerve at his Altar, but the other hath no calling thereunto: and whereas God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <hi>Moſes to aſſemble</hi> 70 <hi>Elaers to beare part of the Government with him,</hi> that was only in temporall affaires, not in Church matters. <hi>Moſes</hi> was overburthened with being both King and Prieſt, of which I have ſhewed you before.</p>
            <p>Secondly, theſe which had any calling or Office to ſerve in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, were inſtated in holy Orders, being conſecrated by the impoſition of hands of the firſt borne, or ſons of Iſrael, the repreſentative Church. But theſe Lay-Elders are not admitted into holy Orders, nor are their hands filled with any thing ſave underhand bribes, which the people to prevent their utter ruine, are forced to give them to purchaſe their favour and friendſhip, in this age of perſecuting tyrannicall Presbyterian Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo that it is evident to any indifferent judgement, that the new created Elders of our dayes, have nothing to doe in our Church as ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Elders. I allowe that there may be in ſeverall States both civill and ſpirituall Elders; but the civill Elders are not to meddle and joyne with ſpirituall in Church affaires, which is the next thing in order I am to treate of.</p>
            <p>There were in Iſrael ſaith Mr. <hi>Godwine</hi> in his Jewiſh Antiquities <hi>fol.,</hi> 197. two Conſiſtories or Courts of juſtice; the one chiefely for Church buſineſſe, the other for the affaires of the Common-wealth: The ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Conſiſtory termed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Synagogue, the ſecular conſiſtory ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Counſell, and this civill Court conſiſted of 71, the odde one being to ſupply the roome of <hi>Moſes</hi> over the firſt 70. Mr. <hi>Purchas</hi> in his Pilgrimage 112, and <hi>Galatinus</hi> conjectures, that in the Counſell
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50637:11"/>that condemned Chriſt, there were the whole number of 71. And as theſe two Courts were ſeverall in their places, remote each from other; ſo were the matters diſcuſſable before them, of ſeverall and diſtinct na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and quallities; as wee may reade in the 2 of Chron. chapter 19. to the ſpirituall Court belonged matters ſpirituall or ceremoniall; to the ſecular Conſiſtory matters civill or criminall; &amp; ſo <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> reforming many abuſes in Church and Commonwealth, firſt appointed throughout all the fenced Cityes of Judah ſecular Judges to determine criminall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and at Jeruſalem he appointed a ſpirituall Court conſiſting of Levites, Prieſts, and the chiefe Fathers of Iſrael: <hi>Amazia</hi> the high Prieſt being chiefe in cauſes ſpirituall for the Lord, and <hi>Zobediah</hi> in cauſes criminall for the King; and this ſpirituall Court was, ſaith Mr. <hi>Godwin,</hi> the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative Church, and had the power of excommunication: hence is that ſaying in Mathew 18.16. <hi>dic Eccleſiae.</hi> This forme of diſtinct government in matters temporall and ſpirituall, is in moſt States of Chriſtendome, and was (till of late the Presbyterian party contrived to bring all into a Chaos) imitated by us in England, wee having ſpirituall and temporall Courts. The one not being to meddle in any matter which properly lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the conuſance of the other; for if they did, from the temporall Court was a writ of prohibition iſſueable to ſtay the proceedings of the ſpirituall: And if it appeared, the matter belonged to the ſpirituall Court, a writ of conſultation was directed forth to the ſpirituall Court to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede in the buſineſſe; ſo that it is manifeſt they were not to joyne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in judicature; for although before in this treatiſe, I have ſhewed you that the high Prieſt did amongſt the Jewes ſit in the Sanhedrin of El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, it was becauſe he was a man excellently learned in the Talmud; for if weele beleeve Mr. <hi>Godwine</hi> he tells us that the high Prieſt ſate there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily, is an errour, for he was not elected into that company, unleſſe he was a man of extraordinary wiſdome, for he was Judge in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, and was not <hi>ex officio,</hi> to meddle in the Sanhedrin; and for my part I cannot find that ever theſe conſiſtories ſate together in one Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, unleſſe Math. 26.3. when they aſſembled to conſpire the death of Chriſt, verſe 5. <hi>they conſulted that they might take Jeſus by ſubtlety and kill him;</hi> and this was decreed by Gods owne will before, he having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of his ſuffrings before them, Math. 16.21. <hi>That he ſhould goe to Jeruſalem, and ſuffer many things of the elders, and Chiefe Prieſts, and Scribes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Imitation whereof ſure this new ſet up motley, medley, conſiſtory, of ours counter-company of Clergy, and Laiety are joyned in one, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50637:11"/>a way to crucifie Chriſts Spouſe: For never were the Saints of God (Chriſts repreſentative Church when aſſembled together) ſo ſcattered, broken, and perſecuted, as they are now (and like to be worſe, ſhould this ſenceleſſe tirany continue) under the hands of cruell ignorant Elders. Things purpoſely called out of the meaneſt of the people, not capable of any ſhame, or ſenſible of any unworthy act, and ſo the fitter to put in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution the unjuſt directions of their imperious Paſtor, and for the undo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of whom he pleaſe, muſt vote to excommunication any one the Parſon privately grudges, Oh rare Rogues!</p>
            <p>Reader pardon my expreſſion, I beleeve I doe not erre in calling them ſo, for they are wandring Jewes and Vagabonds, they pretend they had a paſſe from Geneva to Scotland, and ſo for England, with private di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections to come by Scotland firſt, not becauſe they ſhould not curſe the old Proverb, <hi>Omne malum ab Aquilone:</hi> But becauſe comming from Scotland they would finde the better entertainment in England: It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at this day peopled with a Scottiſh generation, which like ſo many larks dare under the Scotch Hobbies, &amp; in a cowardly feare ſhroud their carcaſes in ruſh-hilles, and there lie, ſuffering the Hobby to ruffe them of all their feathers, ſuch as thoſe would for feare give them the better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement.</p>
            <p>Others for a fooliſh doting upon their Brethren, for they know not what, unleſſe for betraying their Leidge Lord, and Soveraigne, having promiſed him Ayde, which they declined for the tempting pieces of 400000. <abbr>l.</abbr> (for in ſuch a caſe though he was given up into the hands of his friends; yet it was treachery in them) will give them the more hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty welcome, becauſe they came from ſo good a people.</p>
            <p>Now would our grave, wiſe, and honourable Parliament take ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into their ſage conſideration the danger of theſe people remaining a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, who are meer enemies to, and inconſiſtent Rulers in our State, pure Scotch incendiaries, to kindlenew flames amongſts us, that the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen Scot may have another opportunity to warmehis fingers at an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh fire, which is likely to come to paſſe, if theſe malapart Officers be not quickly ſuppreſt.</p>
            <p>Nor can their wiſdomes blame the Chriſtians, who for defence of their juſt freedomes, and liberty of conſcience, without any ſiniſter ends, ſhall cauſe new ſtirs, and in defence of their liberties and Religion, endeavour to chaſe this new tyrany forth of the Kingdome. And I am aſſured would their wiſdomes but duely examine their buſineſſe, heere they would plainely find, it is for no other end. And withall would their grave judgements
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50637:12"/>but ſeriouſly poize the validity of their paſſe to come and ſettle here, they would finde it altogether inſufficient, and no warrant either by Gods Law, or the Law of Nations for ſuch people, by people of other Nations directed hither to ſettle and make a conſtant abode heer: And I am confident their Honours upon due conſideration hereof, would either ſend them from Conſtable to Conſtable backe into Scotland, or elſe whip them quite home to Geneva; which that they may doe.</p>
            <p>The Lord who is Ruler of all mens hearts, dictate this to his ſervants in the Parliament, that they may put their helping hands to this worke, and then the Lord proſper the worke of their hands; Oh proſper thou, ô Lord, their handy worke!</p>
            <p>I will but adde one reaſon more, why the Lay-Elders are not to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in the ſpirituall conſiſtory; and that is, becauſe they were never inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded within the power of the keyes given to the Apoſtles, and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, which power hath from them devolved into our Church.</p>
            <p>Some affirme the Goſpel to have been preached heere by Paul the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle; but I cannot learne any certainety of that: But the Apoſtles being under the perſecution of Nero, I finde that <hi>Philip</hi> and divers of the godly fled into France, who ſevered themſelves aſunder, the better to propogate the Goſpel: about the 64 yeere after Chriſt he ſent over into Brittaine one <hi>Joſephus,</hi> together with one <hi>Simon Zelotes,</hi> to preach unto the Britaines, and adminiſter the Sacraments according to the Rites of the Church of Greece, which <hi>Joſephus,</hi> ſaith <hi>William Malmesbury</hi> in his booke <hi>de Antiquitate Glaſconici Monaſterii,</hi> was buryed at Glaſſenbury; and <hi>John Bale</hi> following the Authority of <hi>Gyldas,</hi> and other Engliſh Writers, ſaith that it was <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea,</hi> and about this time did divers of this Nation receive the Chriſtian faith, and were baptized.</p>
            <p>Not long after all Authors agree that <hi>Lucius</hi> King of this Iſle, ſent to <hi>Eleutherius</hi> Biſhop of Rome <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 177, not promiſing any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to his See, (that not being deſired, only obtruded upon King <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the ſecond in <hi>Beckets</hi> buſineſſe) but to ſay with ſuch as were pricked in minde, Acts 2.37. <hi>Men and Brethren what ſhall wee doe to be ſaved?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eleutherius</hi> underſtanding the deſires of King <hi>Lucius</hi> to be baptized, and to profeſſe and maintaine the Chriſtian Religion, and withall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the able parts and ſufficiency of thoſe two Britaines, <hi>Lucius</hi> had for this purpoſe ſent over to him, did conſecrate them Biſhops, and ſent them backe into Britaine: And withall he taking into conſideration that the converting of ſome, and eſtabliſhing of all of this Iſle in the Chriſtian
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50637:12"/>Faith, was a taske too great for two to undergoe: Though he had know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of their faire progreſſe herein; yet for their eaſe, helpe, and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement in ſo great a worke, he ſent over more labourers after them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Harveſt; who for the better propogating of the faith, and winning of ſoules unto Chriſt, and that all might be inſtructed, they divided the Kingdome into Circuits amongſt them. There being by <hi>Lucius</hi> and his Nobles appointed three ſuperintendents, or Arch-biſhops (inſtead of three Arch-Flamins which ruled before in time of Paganiſme) placed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the reſt; one at London, another at Yorke, another at Carleon in Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth-ſhire. This Biſhopricke of Carleon was after removed thence to St. Davids in Wales, thence into Normandy. Yorke continues Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan ſtill, London was tranſlated to Canterbury by <hi>Auſtine</hi> the Monke. Lambert in his perambulation of Kent <hi>fol.</hi> 63.</p>
            <p>And although the Engliſh Saxons had not received the Goſpel till <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelberts</hi> time, in whoſe Raigne <hi>Gregory</hi> the Pope upon occaſion of ſeeing ſweet faced boyes to be ſould in the Market, and inquiring of them of what Nation and Countrey they were, he was told they were <hi>Angli</hi> and of the Province of Deira, their Kings name being <hi>Alla,</hi> to which <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> replied, well may they be called <hi>Angli à Dei ira liberandi,</hi> to ſing Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujah unto the Lord; whereupon <hi>Auſtin</hi> the Monke was ſent over and preached in Ethelbert his Kingdome to the Engliſh Saxons at Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury, <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 596.</p>
            <p>Yet reverend <hi>Bede,</hi> and divers others teſtifie that the Britons, who by the impetuous fury of the Saxons were beaten hence into Wales, embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Chriſtian faith many hundred yeeres before <hi>Auſtins</hi> time, <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> Perambulation of Kent 19. <hi>Holinſhead</hi> Hiſtory of England 51, and had their Church government by convocations &amp; aſſemblies of the moſt learned and beſt Divines, (which in ſome courſe and order, continued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, till this new faſhioned Presbyters ſtarted up, but never had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Lay-men to joyne with them, in that action, it being conceived not to be warranted by Gods word.</p>
            <p>Some perhaps will wonder at me that I ſhould digreſſe ſo far from my purpoſe for vindication of Biſhops, affirming them to be by <hi>Lucius</hi> our firſt Chriſtian King eſtabliſhed in this Land, I might ſay they were ordained by the Apoſtles themſelves Act. 20.28. but this is no part of my purpoſe; only laid in the way to prove our Church by the Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted heere, ſome ſay by <hi>Paul,</hi> but certaine by <hi>Philip,</hi> and by the Church of Rome in after times (which then was a true Church) much p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:50637:13"/>
            <p>I ſay it is not my purpoſe to vindicate Epiſcopacy, I am too weake a prop to uphold ſuch a tottering and reeling Fabricke: Yet armed inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with truth, outwardly with argument: I will boldly tell you, Reader, (I care not who wonder at me, let them be wondring ſtill, and in their wonder ſnarle at me) I would rather be ſubject to moderate Epiſcopacy, then our Claſſicall Presbytery, ſuch Epiſcopacy as ſhould not Lord it over Gods Heritage; for wee know our Saviour rebuked <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> Mar. 10.42. Luke 22.25. <hi>When the one deſired to ſit to his right hand, the other on his left,</hi> in his Kingdome, ſaying, <hi>The Kings of the Gentiles beare rule over them, and their great ones exerciſe Authority upon them,</hi> but it ſhall not be ſo amongſt you.</p>
            <p>Such Epiſcopacy as ſhould have no temporall honour or office to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw them from their ſpirituall function, there being appointed in every County one Superintendent or Biſhop, who with his Aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of that County ſhould governe the Church, and decree Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Cauſes; I ſay ſuch Epiſcopacy I would rather embrace, and ſubmit unto it, then a company of ignorant Elders; for better it were to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned with prudence and knowledge, then with pride and ignorance, two things incident to our Lay-Elders, and this were agreeable to the word of God, the power of the keyes or of Eccleſiaſticall Authority be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given to the Apoſtles, and their Succeſſors, Apoſtles, and Miniſters, not Lay-Elders; I ſay the power of the keyes being given to all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in generall, not to <hi>Peter</hi> only as is affirmed by <hi>Cajetan</hi> in his book <hi>de primatu Romanae Eccleſiae cap.</hi> 5. and by <hi>Jerome</hi> in his firſt booke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Jovinianus, quod ſine dubio emnes Apoſtoli a Chriſto, &amp; non a Petro ſuſceperunt claves.</hi> And the Holy Ghoſt is plaine in it, whatſoever yee ſhall <hi>bind on earth, ſhall be bound in Heaven,</hi> Math. 18.18. and the 1 of the Corinth. 5.4. <hi>In the name of our Lord Jſeus Chriſt when yee are gathered together, and my spirit, with the power of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to deliver ſuch an one unto Satan, &amp;c.</hi> And Joh. 20.23. Chriſt came and ſtood in the midſt of his Diſciples after his reſurrection, and ſaid <hi>peace be unto you, receive yee the Holy Ghoſt, whoſe ſoever ſinnes yee remit, they are remitted unto them &amp;c.</hi> All which places of Scripture plainely ſhew that the keyes were given to all the Apoſtles in generall, though in the 16 of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew, they were given to <hi>Peter</hi> alone, that is to be underſtood, ſaith one, that <hi>Peter</hi> was to have power over the reſt of the Diſciples, but as to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers their power was all alike. And Chriſt in the 28 of Math. 19. diele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating this power unto the Apoſtles in generall, <hi>bid them goe and teach all
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50637:13"/>Nations,</hi> and verſe the 20. <hi>Loe I am with you even unto the end of the world,</hi> he promiſing his ſpirit to be with them, that is in their ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the worlds end; their Succeſſors though ordained by men, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſame power of juriſdiction the Apoſtles had, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his firſt booke <hi>de Doctrina Chriſtiana,</hi> cap 18. plainely affirmes, <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtas data Apoſtolis &amp; ſucceſſoribus, non data ſuit propter meos, ſed prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Eccleſiaem, qua propter perſeverante Eccleſia poteſtas data Apoſtolis ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet perſeverare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have been a little too tedious in this particular, but Reader your pardon, it was only to ſhew who have Eccleſiaſticall power, and are to medle in the Church, and it is plaine they are the Apoſtles, and their Succeſſors, men lawfully ordained, and having a lawfull calling thereunto, 1 Tim. 3.7.4.14. by the laying on of hands of the presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the firſt borne of Iſrael the repreſentative Church, Acts 6.6. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes 12.23. <hi>not raſhly,</hi> 1 Tim. 5.22. but conſultly <hi>inſtating ſuch in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Orders as are blameleſſe, apt to teach, not covetous, not a Novice, leſt being lifted up with pride, he fall into the condemnation of the Devill,</hi> 1 Tim. 3. he muſt upon examination likewiſe be found to be one, which may be able by ſound Doctrine both to exhort and convince the gainſayers Titus 1.9. and ſuch as theſe being admitted into holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to teach and inſtruct others, have Apoſtolicall power in their Aſſemblies to binde and looſe upon earth, and ſo <hi>dic Eccleſiae,</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the 18 of Mathew the 16. is to be underſtood of men in holy Orders aſſembled together to binde and looſe upon earth, 1 Cor. 5.4. as I have already ſhewed you.</p>
            <p>It doth not follow that every Presbyter in his Pariſh with his Claſſe of Elders hath this power, it were abſurde to alledge it, I have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en you that this power was given to the Apoſtles in generall, and their Succeſſors, and the ſpirituall Conſiſtory muſt conſiſt of ſuch 1 Cor. 5.4.</p>
            <p>Now Lay-Elders can no waies be ſaid Succeſſors to the Apoſtles, they neither being inſtated in holy Orders, nor within the rules pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to be admitted thereunto; unleſſe wee muſt in this topſiturvy time of ours, ſend our grave, wiſe Doctors to the Scoole againe to be taught by ſilly Lay-Elders, which ſcarce know their <hi>A. B. C.</hi> not fit to exhort, much leſſe to convince ſuch, and ſo tread <hi>Antipodes</hi> to the practiſe of the Primitive Churches, obtruding as Laiety no waies claming from Levi to be Rulers and Governours
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50637:14"/>in our Church, ſuch a Laiety as I may juſtly ſay are meere Idols in our Church; ſo that wee have wrought a pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y worke, and brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a fine Reformation; inſtead of Pictures, and Crucifixes in ſtones and windowes, which with much zeale were demoliſhed, wee have placed in our Churches walking Images, things that repreſent El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and which the people worſhip as Elders, but really and truely are none, in the litterall ſence they are not Elders, grave, wiſe, and expert as I have ſhewed you; and admit they were, yet they are Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, not truely Church Officers, as ſpirituall Elders, and are not to joyne with ſpirituall Elders in any Church affaires; ſo that for the people to worſhip them as Elders, or to riſe up before them, is to commit Idolatry; to prevent the occaſion of which, good King <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> cauſed the brazen Serpent (which was ſet up for a good end to heale the people that were bitten of Serpents, Numbers 21.) <hi>to be broken in peeces,</hi> 2 of Kings 18.4.</p>
            <p>In imitation of which good Act, as alſo in commiſeration of the free borne people of England, groaning, under the Tyranny and ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of this worſe then high Commiſſion Court, I hope our happy Parliament who hitherto have ſhewen themſelves ready and willing to redreſſe grievances, will not in this time of neceſſity crying loude unto them for helpe, forget their wonted practiſe of goodneſſe, to relieve diſtreſſed people, and take off the heavy preſſures of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but will rid the people of this one and only grievance in the Kingdome; neither warranted by Gods Law, nor the Lawes of this Kingdome (any further then it is their pleaſures to continue it.) And they will ingage a multitude of prayers for their proſperous procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in all their undertakings; the which that they may ſpeedily doe the Almighty God of Heaven who art a preſent remedy in all diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and a ready helpe at hand for them that are in miſery, the only wiſe God, the great Counſellour, and ruler of all mens hearts, dictate this to his ſervants in the Parliament, that wee may be freed from this intollerable ſlavery to Gods glory, the Parliaments honour, and our owne joy and comfort in the Lord Jeſus, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I briefely couched together ſome collections, and ſhort meditations of mine owne, which to the indifferent, and not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalled judgement will give ſome ſatisfaction in the buſineſſe I have treated of, that theſe fine feathered Buzzards, Lay-Elders, deckt with
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50637:14"/>Eccleſiaſticall Plumes, are meere counterfeits, Semiramis, Elephants which were but ſtuffed oxe hides, which had a gallant undaunted Army in ſuſpence, counterfeit Diamonds, not ſuch as Chriſts Spouſe lookt comely with, Cant. 1 9. Bolton halfe crownes, not lawfully ſtampt with <hi>Caeſars</hi> Image, Scotch twenty-pences, the baſe coyne of a copper Nation, not currant Engliſh, but ſuch as every one may lawfully deny, and I am confident the wiſe and judicious Reader ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly conſidering this will not with the yong Dotterell Birds be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticed with chaffe to be caught in this net, though never ſo privily laied, but will beare off and keepe himſelfe free, till he ſee them fall in their owne miſchiefes, and themſelves caught in the ſhare which they have privily laid for others, and if unadviſedly through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance he hath ſuffered himſelfe to be drawen in to conſent unto this government; yet he will in time unintangle himſelfe from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage thereof.</p>
            <p>As for the perverſe and obſtinate Presbyter which hath wedded the government, together with ſome fat Benefice, and cannot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce himſelfe from the one without leaving the other, having vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perpetuall incumbency to himſelfe; I know his heart is hardened through the deceitfulneſſe of ſin, and I cannot diſwade him from his Claſſicall beneficiall cure: <hi>Let him that is uncleane be uncleane ſtill,</hi> ſpoken to obſtinate and wilfull ſinners; for my part, I doe not ſeeke to waſh Blackmoores, I'le give him leave at his Sunday dinners, and ſpirituall pig-feaſts, when none is by but his Lay-Elders to raile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, and would extreamely thanke the pontificall Parſon would he but write any thing, ſubſcribed with his owne hand in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to what I have here writ, that I might have further occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to anatomize the tyranny of him, and his Elders.</p>
            <p>In the meane time what I have heere writ ſhall ſuffice, hoping ſhortly to heare that this Government will be aboliſhed, ſo that wee ſhall neither neede to wreſtle any longer againſt it in words, nor with <hi>Peter to draw the ſword to cut off the High Prieſt ſervants care Malcus,</hi> who had he lived till now would have beene, Crop the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in this teame of Lay-Elders, but I ſay I hope to ſee theſe Hobby-Horſes unyoked againe before they run to woode with the Church (for they muſt needs goe whom the Devill drives;) And having loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them out of their Eccleſiaſticall Treſſes, wee will turne the Jades to their old Ruſtich drudgeries againe, which will be the better for
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50637:15"/>them, the ſooner it is; becauſe they will the more eaſily come to themſelves againe, and it cannot be worſe for us to ſee them reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med from their wincing conditions, and our ſelves freed from the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill thereof: So that I conclude this worke with an earneſt deſire, that this may ſpeedily come to paſſe, and <hi>Quo citius to Melius.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
